<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Copyright 2023 Nicholas Karpowicz -->
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>io.github.NickKarpowicz.LightwaveExplorer</id>
  
  <name>Lightwave Explorer</name>
  <summary>An efficient, user-friendly solver for nonlinear light-matter interaction</summary>
  <launchable type="desktop-id">io.github.NickKarpowicz.LightwaveExplorer.desktop</launchable>
  <developer_name>Nick Karpowicz</developer_name>
  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>MIT</project_license>
  <content_rating type="oars-1.1" />
  <releases>
  <release version="2024.02" date="2024-02-18" urgency="high">
  <description>
  <p>This release adds the following fixes and improvements:</p>
  <ul>
  <li>FDTD mode now supports importing a user-generated multi-material grid (tutorial upcoming).</li>
  <li>New compressed file format (produces self-contained .zip files).</li>
  <li>Saving and loading of files now done entirely through standard system file dialogs.</li>
  <li>File access now supports XDG portals; Flatpak no longer needs nor requests home folder access.</li>
  <li>Improved interaction with clusters/SLURM script generation.</li>
  <li>Made the user interface more compact and organized.</li>
  <li>Support dynamic loading of new crystal database files.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>
  </release>
  <release version="2023.09" date="2023-09-04" urgency="high">
  <description>
  <p>This release adds the following fixes and improvements:</p>
  <ul>
  <li>Adds a new CPU-based propagation mode on Linux/Windows using C++ std::execution::par instead of OpenMP, which on some computers is nearly twice as fast</li>
  <li>MacOS version now uses Grand Central Dispatch for multithreading, with a slight performance improvement.</li>
  <li>Applies PEMDAS rules to the input arguments of sequence functions. In short: previously an input of 1+2*3 would give 9 because the operators were resolved from left to right, now it has the correct behavior (i.e. 7).</li>
  <li>Multiple small optimizations to propagation kernels with a small (percent-level) performance improvement</li>
  <li>Various bug fixes and stability enhancements (mostly regarding mutex locks).</li>
  <li>A button to collapse the data input panel so that the plots and images fill the whole window</li>
  </ul>
  </description>
  </release>
  <release version="2023.08.04" date="2023-08-15" urgency="high">
  <description>
  <p>This is the initial Flatpak release.</p>
  </description>
  </release>
  </releases>
  <url type="homepage">https://github.com/NickKarpowicz/LightwaveExplorer</url>
  <description>
    <p>
      Lightwave explorer is an open source nonlinear optics simulator, intended to be fast, visual, and flexible for students and researchers to play with ultrashort laser pulses and nonlinear optics without having to buy a laser first. Supports both CUDA and CPU calculations. Its purpose and goals are:
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li>Easily-extensible database of materials</li>
      <li>Multiple physical models, including the unidirectional nonlinear wave equation and finite-difference time-domain approaches.</li>
      <li>Efficient code so that complicated systems can be simulated in 3D: Real laser pulses can be messy, and if they weren't so before a nonlinear crystal, there's a good chance they are after. Multidimensional simulations open up the weird world of spatiotemporal couplings. You have options for very fast simulations when there's a symmetry to use (e.g. cylindrical), alongside fully 3D propagation</li>
      <li>A graphical interface that lets you see what you're doing</li>
      <li>A flexible sequence mode to string together elements: not just nonlinear crystals, also spherical or parabolic mirrors, apertures, filters, free space propagation and more</li>
      <li>Fitting/optimization routines</li>
      <li>A Python module for easy postprocessing</li>
    </ul>
  </description>
  
  <launchable type="desktop-id">io.github.NickKarpowicz.LightwaveExplorer.desktop</launchable>
  <screenshots>
    <screenshot type="default">
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/NickKarpowicz/LightwaveExplorer/master/Documentation/Images/flatpakScreenshot.png</image>
    </screenshot>
  </screenshots>
</component>
